[Music]
hello and welcome to this launch session
I'm Peter with me I have Stefan and
Espen and we're going to talk about
what's new in developer Tools in 2024
release way 1
let's have a look at the session agenda
to begin with Espen will talk about the
ability to have object extensions in the
same application as the base object and
he will also talk about a small tool we
call al2 with some helper functions uh
that you can use in
pipelines then stepan will talk about
improvements to the a language uh
including developer support for co-art
functionality in the
application and then I will take over
talking about uh appsource preview uh
appsource uh hot fix changes as well as
the new inclined appsource gallery that
that replaces the embedded appsource
Marketplace so first let's hear Espen
talk about the ability to have object
extensions in the same app as the base
objects thank you Peter my name is Espen
as you probably know and I'm going to
talking about
and it's actually a a longtime requested
feature that we have now finally
implemented it's all about the ability
to have extension objects in the same
app as the base objects and you can have
multiple extension objects in the same
app this is an Ask we have had for many
years and the idea behind it is that it
will allow you to start do non-breaking
refactoring within an app splitting
objects into modules per
functionality and also prepare for
moving objects into separate apps later
on it is enabling a better design and
separation of concern within the
app and as I said it has been a long
time ask and you may want to know why
didn't we do this before and one of the
answer is the simple one is that we have
been busy with all the functionality but
actually there's a little more to it we
would have liked to do this a long time
ago but we had a big
roadblock and it's all about how we from
the beginning represented tables and
table extensions in the SQL
layer as you can see here if I have a
base app and my app containing a base
object which is my table and I created
two EXT attention to that one and they
will have to be previously in separate
apps when they were deployed in the SQL
Server we would end up having three
tables which will all be joined
together and that join is expensive and
we were afraid to ship a feature that
would allow you to shoot yourself in
both feeds at the same time very
efficiently uh and thereby kill
performance so we didn't want to add it
uh at that
point then something new happened in the
last release because we actually
improved on the SQL layout of tables in
general by having only one table for
companion table which reduces the joints
to
one but in the last release we
actually were focusing on this feature
and could not add the feature that I'm
presenting here to today because if you
collapse all your your table and the
extensions object into the same what we
are now doing in that scenario is that
we actually also collapse it at the SQL
layer so one app with both a table and
multiple table extensions will still
only create one table in SQL layer which
means that there are no joints and the
trick we're doing here is that we are
collapsing the metadata for for the
table so we only generate one table in
the server so there's no cost here of
course if you then in another app add a
um another table extension it will end
up in the companion table and you will
have a single joint so we have sort of
been waiting for getting that idea and
optimizing the um the the existing uh
SQL implementation of table exensions
so what do we support here because we
have many extension objects and actually
we support all of them so enums Pages
reports permission sets and tables can
have base and extension objects in the
same app or you can have multiple
extensions in the same and we support
the combinations one table a table
extensions one page two page
extensions all the
combinations it is enabled by default
when targeting runtime 13 which is the
current release so let's jump to a demo
actually what I have here is a small app
purely for demo
purposes but I this is version two of
the app and in version one I only had
one table one page and one
enum but I'm using appsource cup for
this because we still want to make sure
that you are not Crea creating braking
Extensions by splitting it so we had to
take care of that so if we look at the
table here and if I comment out this
field you can see here at the bottom I
already get a nice message from Absol
cot saying the field with name name and
id2 was found in the previous version
but it's not found in this
version and here below I have a small
table extension within the same
app containing the name field so if
I simply command that back in it
actually fixes my error because now the
surface of this app showing a table with
a table extension with a field called
primary key or PK and name now exist and
I'm not breaking anyone Downstream the
same example
here with a page this case it's an
action I can remove the
action I immediately get told that it is
missing but since I'm doing a small
refactoring I can put it back in here in
the page extension as you can see it
works and we are actually already
uptaking that ourself in this this is
actually from our business Foundation
app where we have the number series
line and there's
actually also a number serious line
obsolete which
is they have isolated the old obsolet
field in the table
extension and you can see there one is
actually extending the other and all of
that is shipping now so we are using
this to refactor and improve our own Bas
app this case business
Foundation but we are going to use this
as
well
so you ask for it now you got
it next
topic this a small tool it's called Al
tool lack of imagination and it is
shipping together with the V6 right next
to your favorite
compiler but don't get too excited
because it's it is a small tool and
right now it only have three different
methods or argument you can call it with
if we don't count the help and the
version it can extract the med the
package manifest from an app file simply
getting out app. Json um and it prints
it to the console so you can pipe it in
wherever you want and use it in a
pipeline you can create a Syle package
basically a package with only symbols
from an existing app file and and you
can get the latest supported Al runtime
version from a platform
version this is built to support our own
pipelines and also BC container
helpers we the reason why we needed this
now is actually because we have removed
the net
4.8 from the binaries which made it hard
to use in a um in
Pipelines
so we created this small tool and right
now it has these three uh kinds of
functionality we may add more in the
future if we need it because now we have
a good place to add small things like
this um and yeah we you can use it we
use it and you will have it in the BC
container
Helper but now you know so
don't oh or think it it's just a small
tune
and Stefan will now present the
next series of new functionality in the
a language over to you Stefan thank you
Espen and yes let's talk about the
language and the changes we've made here
let's start with tool tips on tables we
now have the ability to add tool tips to
tables and you can now reuse tool tips
across all your pages if they are on the
tables and if you have uh code actions
enabled you can also use the new code
action to move tool tips from pages into
tables for isolated storage we add a
support for secret text this means you
can now use the secret text type to get
and set values in isolated storage it's
important to notice here that if you set
a value using secret text then it must
be retrieved using secret text otherwise
you'll get an error for actions you can
now add a specialized file upload action
which enables you to quickly add
functionality to upload one or more
files and for multiple files the upload
file dialogue now supports dropping an
entire folder the trigger for this
action uh specifies a new uh type called
filed upload with this type you can get
the file name and you can get the the
stream for reading the file
content with the work we've done here
we've been working on reference types
and lists for now it works with file
upload and in and outst streams but it
paves the way for future support of
other
types in version 23 we released the
prompt dialog page type for Designing
co-pilot
experiences it has specific areas for
creating prompts for the produced
outcome and for tweaking with adding
additional options it also includes
system actions that you can Implement
for attaching additional data to The
Prompt for generating regenerating and
controlling the co-pilot
experience this gives you a recognizable
co-pilot dialogue with all the options
that you
need but now we've added prompt guides
to the action area of prompt
dialogues in these actions you can
specify scenarios that the user can use
to be inspired to create uh new prompt
values to get data from the system or
just be inspired to try out new
things for other Pages like lists we now
have a prompting action area in this
area you can Define new actions that are
related to co-pilot experiences the
first visible action in the prompting
area will be shown on the page on top of
all the content for quick
access as with other action areas you
can organize your actions in
groups you can also find the list of
co-pilots prompting ctions in the action
bar and here you can also turn off the
quick action overlay on pages you can
also now use instructional text on
fields this gives you the ability to
hint at the user what data needs to be
in the field if there's no value in it
yet it is supported on text based
Fields if you're working with external
Services we now made it easier for you
to work with
cookies with the cookie type you can now
set cookies on requests and read them
from responses and you can even
automatically use the response cookies
for the lifetime of the HTP client
instance this is very useful for
connecting to services with cookie based
sessions number sequence has been
enhanced with a restart method and a
range method the range method allows you
now to get a whole range in a single
database call enabling for much more
performant bulk operations
we've added new obsolete States pending
move and moved and two new properties
moved from and moved to this is part of
our efforts to make refactoring between
extensions easier you can find examples
of this in the number series module it
was moved from the base application to
the business Foundation
application moving is imported on tables
and Fields And by using this we can
remove the need for data copy in code
using this method we do not consider it
a breaking change and if the consumer
already have the move table in
scope then an uptake is not needed it
will simply work
seamlessly the functionality is
currently limited to a select set of
applications but we intend to open up
for everyone to use this in the
future we recognized a need for the app
Json to contain comments so now you can
change the language mode on your app
Json file to Jason with comments and add
your own
notes I'll end here with an important
update we have been upgrading the
debugger in the vs code Al language
extension this means we no longer can
support debugging on Services running
older versions of business
Central if you need to debug an older
version you must install an older
version of the a language extension you
can do this from vs code or from the PC
images talking about debugging Peter you
also have an important update yes thank
you Stefan so another feature that
Partners have been asking for for a long
time has been the ability to debug this
system
application and so have you also missed
that well now you finally can so just
set break points uh in code and in in
the system application code or steep
into it and debug the system
application uh note though that we are
still respecting the non debuggable and
the secure text uh that will limit
debugging in protected areas of the
system application so the major benefits
uh of this is that when you are
developing and troubleshooting your own
applications that call into the system
app you can now debug into the system uh
app as well also if you and I hope you
are contributing um via open source uh
to the system application you can now
actually debug those contributions
yourself uh in Cloud so that's sort of
empowering your work there now the
reason for not enabling this sooner uh
has been that it required multiple
platform features including the Recently
Added secure text that Stefan just uh
talked about uh if you want to know more
about the secure text I mean you could
see that but you could also uh uh watch
the launch recording from the last
release so let's switch gear to the
first uh of a couple of appsource
improvements and we'll start out with
appsource
preview so we now support the appsource
preview State uh which all submitted
apps automatically go to when passing
validation so that means that as a
publisher you can release uh your app
directly uh you know to public uh
visibility in the appsource marketplace
as usual but now you can also keep it in
preview and actually uh create and share
a link to that preview app which you can
uh either use yourself or you can send
it to selected customers uh for instance
for um allowing them to install it as
maybe a fast hot fix uh validation or a
limited go live among a few uh customers
uh to to verify that everything works
before you scale out I mean you can even
use this to test yourself in a in a in
your own uh production or sandbox
environments in cloud and this allows
you to ensure that your app is ready for
prime time before releasing it to all of
your
customers now as I mentioned uh
customers administrators you know
Consultants behaving as delegated admins
can install the preview versions and we
support sandbox
environments um I think I made a said
production just before to test it out
but we actually only support uh
production uh for now uh also uh the
preview support is uh something that we
actually uh shipped in the 203 release
or 20 2023 release wave uh 2 uh minor um
so we kind of you know backported it uh
in that
now to identify a preview version
partner Center operates with a concepts
of a a preview audience and a a height
key which we actually call a preview key
because that we think fits better with
with the feature and you might actually
also in a partner Center documentation
or appsource documentation see uh the
word flight key being used for this now
in partner Center on your app in this
case we have the Bing apps um sample in
partner Center uh you can under the
preview audience Define yourself a
preview key but if you don't do that one
will uh be generated by the system
system right so that that's that's
basically always going to be a a preview
key but probably you want to have
something that is humanly
readable now then to allow customers to
install or you know admins to install
your preview version you then need to
share a link with them uh and that link
needs to contain the tenant ID for the
customer environment the app ID and then
the preview key and so you can see here
an example uh I highlighted the the
three parameters I just mentioned but um
note that you can only install via this
link today there is actually in the
partner uh Center a link but you cannot
use that to install at this point and
you also cannot log into app Source
Marketplace and install a preview
version not until it becomes public now
installing uh with this link is kind of
business as usual except that in the
install dialogue we will tell now user
that this is a preview version that they
are installing also if you're trying to
install this in a production environment
that will fail
today so there's a couple of things uh
that are good to know for appsource
Publishers so first off um it's not
possible to install a version of an app
that is lower uh than the latest
publicly uh available version of that
app for business Central um so so if if
you launch a preview or if you want to
create a preview version you need to
have a higher version than the last
public
version um also as I mentioned before if
you want to use uh a preview you have to
set a preview key uh as part of the
marketplace submission process and you
have to send it be set it before you
submit you can't submit and then go in
and add the preview key for the same
version of the app and expect it to work
have to do it as part of the submit uh
process also we do support having
simultaneously simultaneous previews uh
with different versions and potentially
different preview Keys uh that will be
supported so you could uh basically you
know send different links to different
customers or maybe they're not sort of
on the same Cadence with this but um
partner Center itself will only show the
the last submission right and if you at
some point take one of those preview
versions and move into public then that
is the one that will be shown but the
the links will still uh
work
um yeah then we understand that as part
of the preview process and this is one
of the the big benefits of the preview
process also is that you probably want
to react to the feedback that you are
getting from your customers uh so you
are actually allowed to make breaking
changes between preview versions um and
actually what happens is that we are
always using Force sync when we are uh
upgrading uh previews from one version
uh to another that of course means that
there could be data loss between
previews but U they're right now
supposed to run on sandboxes and for
sort of testing out this functionality
so that that ought to be okay of course
your apps still need to when you go to
public they need to be uh compliant with
the sort of previous version and going
forward as well then if you have a
dependencies for your preview apps uh
maybe even to uh to preview um libraries
then you have to include those uh as
required and also it's important to
mention that the preview feature is
really only for um you know creating
these pre-releases and verifying that
the quality is good enough they are not
in intended for creating specific
customer apps one of customer apps where
you you know give a specific customer
link and they have their own app or for
a general sort of trial version that
people can use so that's important to
keep in mind also for administrators uh
installing these apps um as I mentioned
we only support sandboxes at this point
so technically we actually also support
production but we launch with sandbox
only to manage risk and to get feedback
and honestly I think also the core
scenario is really for testing out and
likely you want to test this out in a
sandbox a customer would like to test
out the new functionality in sandboxes
to not incur any production
disturbances this also implies that um
sandbox uh sandbox environments that
have a preview version installed they
cannot be copied to or restored to
production environments right and so if
you want to do that
you need to either replace that preview
version with a later or newer public
version or you have to uninstall the
preview app
right then uh preview versions uh can be
updated to a higher uh preview version
and to do that you use the uh link that
I mentioned before or you can update
them to a public version once that comes
out right and you do that in the admin
Center or you can even use the link
there as well but without the the the
preview
key uh when uh your environment is
updated uh your preview versions will be
updated to any newer public version
based on your preferences uh for major
and minor objects basically just
business as usual in
this and then whenever operations are
done on extensions we have Telemetry and
in that Telemetry we actually now
indicate whether the uh extension uh was
a preview extension or not so we have
extension availability and extension
preview key provided dimensions in a
couple of the Telemetry signals that
allows you to go in and understand or
monitor uh what has been
installed if you want to know more about
uh this uh functionality we have I put
in here a link to the fact uh we also
have docs in the administration for
managing uh this there is a small video
covering it and we also have the release
note so now over to uh another feature
uh appsource app hot fixes so in uh 2023
release wave 1 we added the ability to
hot fix appsource apps that Target older
versions of business Central that used
to be a problem because we saw a lot of
Partners not being able to adopt uh or
release appsource apps for a new
business center release because that
will prohibit them from um from hot
fixing existing customers but we sold
that a couple of releases ago um and
then to ensure that customers could
actually be upgraded from that hot fix
version to the latest um or next version
available in appsource we validated the
hotfix version
against this next version but only the
first version of that app targetting you
know the next uh business Central minor
minor minor minor release and we re
received a lot of feedback uh from uh
Partners on ideas that they would like
to validate against the latest version
instead and so um in 2023 release Wave 2
we sort of backported it to that H we
changed the validation so that we now do
validate against the latest appsource
app version and that um has the benefit
that it ensures compliance with the
latest version of that app at the time
of hot fix that previous version that
also allows Partners to perform more
changes uh in their hot fix version
right so for example a common scenario
is that Partners can Now backport
features and include them in the hotfix
version if there are no breaking changes
to the latest version right they
couldn't do that before because uh if
they wanted to both add this to the
latest version and to the hot fix and
the validation of the hot fix was to the
first version without that additional
you know functionality we would say that
the hot fix was introducing something
not in the later version and that would
break
validation if you want to know more
about this it sounds complicated maybe
but uh I put in a link to uh to the docs
on
that let's talk about seeing and
installing appsource apps directly
inside of the business Central uh web
client uh so in addition to the primary
uh appsource Marketplace site online
business Central has for many releases
had an embedded appsource experience
inside of the client and you could use
that uh to browse um all of the apps uh
available for business Central in a
fairly rudimentary way and you could
open up a card uh for that app read more
about it see marketing material etc etc
however uh this embedded appsource
experience has been deprecated by the
appsource team from uh basically now
April 2024 and it's been replaced with
um with apis that allows customer
experiences for surfacing appsource app
Marketplace content within the hosting
application and given its widespread use
uh in business Central by partners and
customers to browse and install apps we
have uh decided to replace the old embed
experience with a new experience that we
call uh Microsoft appsource
apps and this is the experience uh in
its first version uh so uh first and
most importantly this list provides a
much stronger uh capability to search
and filter than before you I mean if you
just saw that list just a few slides
before I can show it here again this is
not a great search experience right and
but here you can search uh filter Etc
and you can use it it in a way uh
basically as a standard list page right
view sort filter we also show both the
name the publisher name the install
State popularity rating number ratings
and last modified date so you can
actually filter down to this also uh we
give you the ability to jump uh to the
Online appsource Marketplace in a
browser uh or even jumping uh to that
specific app that you highlighted in the
list in the Online appsource
Marketplace and there Al there's also an
edit user settings that allows you to
switch uh your Regional language to
influence what is being showed or
filtered in this list to match uh those
settings of course you can select uh one
of the apps in this case uh we are
looking at the Shopify connector and
just as before we show a cart where you
can see additional information and Link
Etc we are not showing images at least
not at this point though because that's
a you know fairly heavy process to to
get through the API and we want this to
render as fast as
possible you can still install from this
card uh if the app is free or have a
transact plan you of course still need
to purchase on appsource and for other
cases like contact me you need to go to
appsource and install there for
now let's uh have a small demo of this
experience experience okay so here we
are in the web client and so let's uh go
and just uh search for uh our appsource
page right so we have the Microsoft
appsource apps
page and it lists all of the apps and
you can see that the list is quite
extensive right we can scroll through uh
we can of course filter uh let's see you
know what apps are coming out of
Microsoft for example if I can
spell
it so here we see all of the apps uh
from Microsoft H you know we can scroll
through them uh we can uh sort them by
uh by last modified date maybe we
probably want to have the descending one
to see the newest on top of course we
can sort it by name we saw before that
we opened the Shopify connector so just
as before we can uh read the uh details
on this we can jump and show it uh in
appsource if we want to see the full
experience in there and there's another
thing that you can do you know this can
be a long list so want I take the
advantage of the analysis mode and so uh
inside of the analysis mode uh you can
for example uh group all the apps uh by
the publisher for instance here I fill
it to Microsoft maybe that's not so
interesting but if you have a lot of of
different Publishers uh or you know
rating or things like that you can
actually uh group according to that and
yes I showed uh how you can filter and
slice extensions in the analysis mode H
you can actually even uh you know use
the uh the new co-pilot uh experience
for the uh analysis mode to just in
natural language uh ask it to help how
you uh want to view um in the analysis
mode your extensions maybe not the most
advanced scenario but it is
supported okay there's actually a little
bit more here right a few things first
of all um last year we launched the
ability to sell your apps through
appsource Marketplace and you can join
me and Kurt to learn more about that we
have a a session what's new selling your
business Central apps using the
Microsoft commercial
Marketplace also we have a super
exciting a new tool called page
scripting that allows customers and
Consultants to easily uh record and play
user acceptance tests directly in the
business Central web client driving
higher test cost driving higher test
coverage increase agility while reducing
costs uh this is something that we
release as a preview in 2024 release way
1 and you can uh join me in a session
going deep into this uh the in preview
use acceptance testing with the new page
scripting tool and finally we have a lot
of updated um documentation content for
Developers for data analytics reporting
word uh layouts in special error
handling uh troubleshooting tools and
guides uh you know acing processing
Telemetry security extensibility and how
you can help adding to the documentation
and so Kenny will host a session just on
this the what's new key updates in
learning content for
developers so as usual you have a a lot
of different uh channels or resources
where you can give us feedback or ask
questions um you can submit ideas as
well that's all for now thank
you